你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到PWN学院
welcome to pwn college
我是Yan
I'm Yan
在今天的视频中
and today in this video
我们将要讨论
we're going to be talking about
汇编中的寄存器
registers in assembly
好的
all right
我们在之前的视频中讨论过数据
we talked about data in the previous video
cpu喜欢数据
and CPUs love data
他们处理数据
they process data
二进制数据
binary data
CPU会用多种方式解析它，让我们理解
that is interpreted in various ways that make sense to us
现在CPU需要一个地方来存储这些数据
now a CPU needs somewhere to store that data
一个暂时的存储空间
short term memory
你可以把数据想象成钱
if you will you imagine data as money
CPU手里有一堆钱
and the CPU's handed a bunch of money
它可能会把钱放到收银机里
it might put it in a cash register
它在计算机世界里被称为寄存器堆
and what is called in the computing world the register file
现在，寄存器堆位于CPU内部
now the register file sits right inside of the CPU
有一堆寄存器
and holds a bunch of registers
基本上数据是从系统内存中流出
and basically data flows from system memory
进入各级缓存
into some various caches
不幸的是英文名和收银机冲突了
unfortunate name collision there with cash register
也许这不是一个很好的类比
maybe it's not a great analogy
然后流进要用它的寄存器堆
and then into the register file where it is used
或者数据直接从指令流入到寄存器堆
or it flows directly from the instructions into the register file
稍后会讲到，再流进寄存器
as we will talk into registers
什么是寄存器
what are registers
寄存器是快速存储数据的地方
registers are fast places to store data
它们用于
they are meant for very
这是CPU唯一可以交互的地方
it's the only place that the CPU can typically
这么说不对
that's false
通常，CPU在这个位置存储数据
it is the typical place to store data for a CPU
与这些数据交互
to actually interact with that data
对它进行操作
to make to do operations on it
对它进行计算等等
to do computation on it etc etc
它们的速度非常快
they are extremely fast
它们就在CPU里
they're right in the CPU
所以没有很大的空间给它们
and so there's not a lot of space for them
它们制作起来非常昂贵
they're very expensive to make and
所以它们的数量很少
so there's very few of them
取决于体系结构
depending on the architecture
如果你经历过很久之前
if you were living way back
英特尔推出8086或8085处理器时
when Intel gave the world the 8086 or 8085 even
只有8个寄存器
via just 8 of them
实际上只有7个
in fact just 7
现在我们的情况好多了
nowadays we are much better off
AMD扩充英特尔x86架构
AMD when they expanded intel x86 architecture
到64位x86架构时
into the 64 bit x86 architecture
也称为AMD64
also known as AMD64
以他们无限的智慧
in their infinite wisdom
给我们提供了大量的寄存器
they gave us an enormous amount of registers
以用于存储数据和计算
which we can use to store data and do computation
还有很多特殊寄存器
there are also a lot of special registers
例如，存储下一条指令地址的寄存器
registers for example that store the address of the next instruction
我们将在以后的视频中讨论它
we'll talk about that in a future lecture
还有其它用于多媒体计算的寄存器
and then other very fancy stuff for multimedia computation
我在上一讲中提到过
that I mentioned in a previous lecture
我们可能再也不会提起这件事了
we probably never really talk about it again
好的
okay so
寄存器驻留在CPU中
registers live in your CPU
它们的大小通常就是架构的字长
they are the size of the word width of the architecture typically
当然也有很多例外
right again exceptions abound
但在64位架构上
but on a 64 bit architecture
大多数寄存器都是64位的
most of your registers are going to hold 64 bits
就是8个字节，每个字节8位
that is 8 bytes of 8 bits each
您可以通过名称访问寄存器
you can access registers by their name
或通过部分标识符访问其中的一部分
or you can access parts of them by partial identifiers
这很酷
and this is really cool
这反映了，至少是x86，架构的历史
this reflects the history of the architecture of at least an x86
RAX是64位x86寄存器
RAX is the 64 bit x86 register RAX
它代表，我记不清了，但好像是
it stands for I don't remember but let's say
R表示很，x表示扩展
Really extended extended A
好吧
all right
它是多次进化的最终结果
now that's because it is the end result of a lot of evolution
计算机架构的字长不断增长
that keeps growing the word width of the architecture
在英特尔8085时代
back in the old Intel 8085 days
8085是一个8位的架构，有一个寄存器a
the 8085 was a 8 bit architecture that had a register A
英特尔把8085升级到8086时
when the 8085 was evolved into the 8086 by Intel
它变成了一个16位寄存器，叫做A已扩展，AX
it became a 16 bit register called A eXtended AX
你能单独使用ax的一部分
you could reference the individual parts of ax
即2字节16位寄存器的，各个字节
the individual bytes of this 2 byte 16 bit register
分别叫AH和AL
with AH and AL
AL是原来的A
right so AL was the old A
它接上了AH，做成了AX
ah was tacked onto it to make ax
因特尔创建386，还是286
when Intel created 386 or 286 I guess
也许是186，我不确定
maybe even 186 I don't know that for sure
他们扩展了16位寄存器ax
they extended the 16 bit register ax
到32位寄存器eax
into the 32 bit register extended ax
你依旧可以用原来的小部件
and you could still reference the old smaller parts of it
等AMD扩展了因特尔x86成amd64时
and when AMD extended Intels x86 into AMD 64
现代64位x86架构
the modern 64 bit x86 architecture
他们很用力的把eax拉伸成了64位的rax
they really stretched eax into RAX 64 bit
x86上的寄存器都可以直接使用其部分
every register on x86 can be partially referenced
但只有这些老的寄存器
but only these old historic ones
可以直接用右数第二字节
can you get at that old second byte from the right
但都可以直接用右数第一字节
but all of them you can get at the right most byte
最右边两个字节
at the right most two bytes
最右边4个字节
the right most 4 bytes
和完整的8字节64位寄存器
and the full 8 byte 64 bit register
很酷
pretty cool huh
好的
alright
这就是寄存器
so that's register
它们保存着数据
they hold data
但是我们怎么把数据放进去呢
but how do we put data in them
我们可以用汇编指令mov
well we do so with an assembly instruction mov
我们可以
we just say hey
将数字0x539移动到RAX中
move the number 0x539 into RAX
像这样
and we write it like this
mov rax, 539
mov rax comma 539
就像你在数学课上写x = 7一样
the same way that you write x equals 7 or something in a math class
数据流向是
the flow of data is
在你的屏幕上，是这个方向
in your screen that way
从1337到RAX
it goes from 1337 to RAX
第二行就是到RBX
or RBX in the second line
它俩都被设置为一个值了
they both get set to the same value
一个是16进制表示
one value is specified in hexadecimal
第二行是十进制表示
the equivalent value on the next line is in decimal
在汇编指令中直接指定的数据
data that's specified directly in an assembly instruction
我猜这是你们第一次看到完整的汇编指令
so I guess this is the first assembly instruction you've fully seen
非常简单，对吧?
super simple right
它就是把数字1337放入RAX
it just puts the number 1337 into RAX
像这样指定的数据
data that is specified like that
数字1337被称为立即数
number 1337 is called an immediate value
它立即取一个1337，把它放到寄存器RAX中
so it takes an immediate 1337 puts it in the register RAX
当然你也可以
you can also of course
用我们讲的部分寄存器
we talked about partial registers
你可以访问这些
well you can access those
你可以把5放到AH
you can say hey move 5 into ah
然后将0x39放到AL
and then moves 0x39 into AL
这会在RAX中创建0x539
which will create 0x539 in RAX
也就是1337
which is 1337
太酷了
super cool alright
要注意一件事
be careful one thing
你可以访问AH
you can access ah
你可以访问AL
you can access al
彼此互不干扰
very independent of each other
它们只修改RAX的对应位
and they'll all just go into the respective bits of RAX
如果你碰了EAX
if you touch EAX
RAX的32位部分
the 32 bit part of RAX
最右边的32位
the right most 32 bits
它会把寄存器里剩下的32位清零
it's gonna zero out the rest of the register
信不信由你
all right believe it or not
这是出于性能考虑
this is done for performance reasons
原因非常复杂
that are very complicated
感兴趣的话，它应该和计算机架构有关
should take computer architecture if you're interested
但这确实会发生，而且很搞人
but it will happen and it'll screw you up
它实际上使
and it actually makes
在64位环境中写32位代码有点棘手
writing 32 bit code in 64 bit context a little tricky
因为如果你碰了一个地址
because if you touch a address which tends to
我们有点超前了
anyways we're getting ahead of ourselves
如果你改了EAX
if you touch EAX
rax会被修改（包括高32位）
rax will be clobbered
如果你改了EBX
if you touch EBX
那么RBX的前32位将被破坏
then the top 32 bits of RBX will be clobbered
以此类推
and so on
好了现在
alright now
如何转移数据
how do you shunt data around
如同从指令转移到寄存器
while you move between instruction
那样把0x539放到rax中
in the same way that you can move 0x539 into RAX
这行代码mov rbx, rax
this line mov RBX comma RAX
将数据从RAX移动到RBX
moves the data from RAX into RBX
我说的移动是指复制
now I say move I mean copy
旧数据不会被销毁
the old data is not destroyed
这有点奇怪，就提一嘴
so it's a weird little bit of a weird caveat
我觉得他们是考虑到了这条mov
I think they really optimize for this mov
因为，销毁立即数没有意义
because then  it doesn't make sense how do you copy an immediate value
你可以
because you could
不管怎样
but anyways
mov不会破坏mov的数据源
move does not destroy the source of the move
它只是将数据复制到目标地
it just copies that data into the destination
目的地在左边
the destination is on the left
数据源在右边
the source is on the right
你也可以在部分寄存器之间mov
and you can also move between the partial registers
只要尺寸一致就行
as long as the sizes line up
我们稍后会讲到
we'll get to that later
你可以将数据mov到寄存器的部分
you can move into the partial registers
用起来是一样的
and it looks the same
但请记住
just keep in mind
修改EBX时
any time you write to EBX
剩下的32位
the remaining 32 bit
或者说修改任意寄存器的低32位
or any of the lower 32 bit of the registers
剩下的32位
the remaining 32 bit
寄存器的高32位
the high 32 bits of that register
会被清零
will be zeroed out
别被这个搞了
don't let it screw you up
现在假设你想扩展数据
now let's say you wanted to actually extend
你把-1放到eax
you wanted to move negative 1 to eax
你想要的是
which you wanted that to be like
它和64位寄存器中的-1一样
you know actual negative 1 in 64 bit
默认情况下不是
by default it's not
默认情况下
by default when you look at it
如果把- 1放到EAX，就是fffffffffff
if you move negative 1 to EAX that's fffffffffff
这也许是正确的补码
maybe that was the right number of it in 2's complement
它既是42.9亿，也是-1
that's both this 4.29 billion and negative one
但在rax中
but rax
因为高32位会被清零
since the top bits are all zeroed out
它就只是42.9亿
it's only that high number
不再是-1了
it is not 0 1 anymore
这很遗憾
that's a bummer
很不好
not great
如果我们在做数学运算
if we are doing some math
开始时用32位操作
and then we'll be starting run the 32 bit stuff
然后用64位寄存器操作这些值
and then we need to access those same values on 64 bit
这真的会毁了我们的一天
this could really ruin our day
如果你想把32位的-1扩展成64位的-1
if you want to extend that negative 1 into 64 bit negative 1
有一个基于mov的指令movsx
there's another instruction that's based as move and sign extend
它可以
it'll move the thing
它会检查
and then it'll look
如果是负的
if it's negative
它会将剩下的这些0置1
and it'll put ones everywhere to make the remaining number 0
使用movsx rax, eax
with that with movsx rax EAX
你先将-1放到eax
so you move negative 1 to EAX
rax的高32位被清零
the left 32 bits of RAX are zeroed out
然后取EAX，将符号扩展到RAX
then you take EAX and you move sign extended into RAX
这把寄存器的值放到它自己的位置
that's taking the register and moving it into itself
是有效的
totally valid
它会扩展符号
it'll sign extend
保留补码
preserve the 2's complement value
然后得到一个漂亮的64位的-1
and give you a beautiful 64 bit negative 1
酷
very cool
若你好奇，现在你知道了
alright just now you know if you were ever curious
你能mov很多数据
you can move a lot of data
你可以在寄存器中对数据做很多操作
or you can do a lot of operations on data in registers
这里有一些你可以做的有趣的事
here is just some of the many cool things you can do
你可以加
you can add
减
you can subtract
自增、自减
you can increment then decrement
就是加1、减1
that's add 1 and subtract one
有很多类似这种的操作
there's a lot of these sort of little like
不是必须的辅助指令
helper instructions that aren't strictly necessary
显然你可以用add rax, 1
obviously you could just add rax 1
而不用inc rax
instead of inc rax
但现在就是有
but here we are
可以or、xor、左移、右移
you can or xor shift left and right
往下还有很多
and you can read more and more and more
有一个很酷的工具叫rappel
actually there's a really cool tool called rappel
它预装在PWN学院的做题环境中
it's preinstalled in the pwn college dojo
它能让你写汇编指令
it just allows you to write assembly and it'll
它会运行指令，然后展示寄存器的变化
just run that binary and show you how the registers changed
非常酷的东西
very cool stuff alright
你可以做很多事情
a lot of things you can do
有一条指令不在这里
one instruction that's not on here
应该加在这里的
that I realized should be on here
交换指令，xchg
exchange xchg exchange
你给它两个寄存器
you give it two registers
它会交换它们的值
and it swaps their values
酷
very cool all right awesome
你可以在寄存器上做很多算术运算
so a lot of things you can do arithmetically on registers
有些寄存器你不能或不应该操作
some registers you can't or shouldn't do stuff to
比如rip
for example rip
它保存着下一条指令的地址
which is the address of the next instruction
我们会讲到
we'll actually talk about
如何得到这个值
how to get that value
以及如何改变它等等
and how to change it and so forth
先别担心
don't worry about it yet
另一个特殊寄存器RSP
another special register RSP
它包含了内存中称为栈的特殊区域的地址
it contains the address of a special region called the stack in memory
也先别担心它
don't worry about that yet
我们下节课会讲
we'll talk about that in the next lecture
还有一些其它的重要寄存器
and there are other registers that are used about for important things
我们以后也会讲到
that we'll also talk about it later
但是一般来说
but you know generally speaking
寄存器很酷
registers are cool
你可以用它们来计算
you can use them to compute
还有很多其他疯狂的寄存器
there are also a lot of other crazy registers
我想我已经提过好几次了
I think I have mentioned this several times
用于处理大量数据计算的寄存器
in terms of registers that are used for big data crunching
还有操作系统自身使用的特殊寄存器
there are also special registers that are used by the operating system itself
我们将在后面的模块中讨论这个
we will talk about this in later modules
这将是令人震惊的
it is going to be mind blowing
很令人兴奋的东西
super exciting stuff
因特尔带来的
brought to you by I guess Intel
寄存器和像你们这样的令人兴奋的观众
registers and viewers like you
下次再见
see you next time